Dear fellow practitioners, with a mindful and contemplative attitude,
Kính thưa các quý Đạo Hữu để tâm chiếu
I wish you all
Hoàn quán chúc các quý đạo hữu
much enlightenment during
à được nhiều sự giác ngộ trong mùa Tu An
this Summer Retreat. I am also
Cư kiết hạ này tâm chiếu Hoàn quán cũng
very happy to have the opportunity to study the
rất là hoan hỉ khi mình được
Dharma in the practice sessions during
à Trạch Pháp trong các cái bài tu trong
this retreat.
chương trình an cư kiết hạ này thì Kính
Dear fellow practitioners, I
thưa các quý đạo hữu tâm chiếu hn quán
share that when I practiced the Six Harmonies, I
chia sẻ khi mà tâm chiếu Hàn quán tu Lục
saw so
Hòa ấy thì tâm chếu Hàn quán thấy nó có
much merit—so much merit! I
nhiều công đức quá thôi nhiều công đức
truly didn't expect the
lắm lắm tâm chiếu quán thật là không ngờ
merit of the Six Harmonies to be so great.
Công Đức Lục Hòa nó lại lớn đến mức độ
For example, when I
như vậy đâu Ví dụ trong cái lúc mà tâm
told you all, "
chếu H Quán bạch cho các quý đạo hữu đấy
This family practices like this, but if we practice the Six
nhà này tu như thế này nhưng nếu tu Lục
Harmonies and dedicate the merit like this," I already
Hòa nó hồi hướng như này tâm chế quán đã
felt so happy. I saw
thấy hoan hỉ quá rồi Tức là thấy nó được
so much merit! But then, when I
quá nhiều Phước luôn rồi thế nhưng mà
asked the students to gather all the
bảo các em là đi tập hợp cho cô tất cả
sutras about the Six Harmonies, when they
các bài kinh nói về Lục Hòa thì đến lúc
read them, the merit was truly unimaginable, so
đọc vào thì lại đúng là công đức không
immense, beyond our comprehension.  The
quá lớn như thế nó ngoài cái sự tư duy
merits I'm currently experiencing in practicing the Six Harmonies are
cái mình đang thấy về Công Đức Lục Hòa
still very small compared to the true merits
nó còn rất là nhỏ so với công đức thật
of the Six Harmonies that arise during
của Lục Hòa nó phát sinh ra trong quá
our practice, dear fellow practitioners. It
trình chúng ta tu Lục Hòa các quý đạo
generates so much merit
hữu ạ Nó phát sinh ra quá nhiều công đức
and wisdom, so much good fortune.
và trí tuệ luôn quá nhiều Phước báo
Those who practice the Six Harmonies receive the protection and support of all the
người tu Lục Hòa được tất cả chúng chư
celestial beings and gods; they
thiên chư thần người ta đều phát tâm hộ
all rejoice and are mindful of their actions.
Trì ủng hộ người ta đều hoan hỉ tâm chế
Seeing this, one might think that
hn quán thấy như thế thì mình cứ nghĩ là
one is diligently practicing the Six Harmonies due to the accumulation of
mình cũng tinhh tấn nục Hòa rồi do nhiều
merit, but it turns out that simply practicing diligently and
công đức nhưng hóa ra là cứ tu tinh tấn
steadfastly is enough to achieve that, dear
nục Hòa là đã được cái đấy rồi các quý
practitioners. It's
Đạ hiểu ạ đã được các vị hộ trì rồi chứ
not that one has to keep practicing until there's something
không phải là mình cứ rồi có cái là một
else, and that's what's truly amazing, dear fellow
cái này nữa mới lại là hay chứ các quý
practitioners. It means that even if someone practices the
Đạ Hữu hay lắm cơ tức là người này dù tu
Six Harmonies, they may not
Lục Hòa nó chưa hẳn là đã biết tu Lục
fully understand it, but simply by
Hòa hẳn nhưng mà chỉ cần
liking it and persevering in practicing it, they will be
này thích tu Lục Hòa và kiên tâm tu Lục
reborn in the
Hòa thôi mà chết đã được sinh lên cung
Heaven of the Great Realm. That's the Heaven where
trời Đâu xất rồi Cung trời mà Bồ Tát hộ
our Bodhisattvas reside, where
minh của chúng ta ở trên đấy trên đấy có
all the Bodhisattvas who have attained enlightenment in this life are
tất cả các Bồ Tát nhất sinh bổ xứ đang
practicing.  Up there, until the final life,
tu ở trên đấy để đến kiếp cuối cùng đi
descending here, we only need to not abandon the
xuống đây chỉ cần chúng ta không bỏ pháp
practice of the Six Harmonies, my dear fellow practitioners.
tu Lục Hòa Thôi các quý đạo hữu ạ cái
Our hearts must be steadfast in wanting to practice the
tâm của chúng ta kiên định muốn tu pháp
Six Harmonies. We don't count the
Lục Hòa thôi còn không tính trong quá
misunderstandings or mistakes we make during our practice. That's
hiểu mà chúng ta làm không đúng nhá
not counted. It's just about having a steadfast heart in
Không tính cái đấy chỉ là cái tâm kiên
practicing the Six Harmonies, my dear fellow practitioners. And when we
định tu Lục Hòa Thôi các quý đạo hữu ạ
die, if we maintain this from now
mà chết chúng ta cứ giữ như thế từ giờ
until the end of our lives, we will be reborn in the Tushita
đến cuối đời chết sẽ được sinh lên Cung
Heaven. Oh my, reading that, it's
trời đâu xuất Ui giời đọc tới đấy Thì
truly unimaginable, my dear fellow
đúng là nó thực sự là không thể nghĩ bàn
practitioners! And the words of the Buddha lead
các quý đạo hữu ạ Mà lời Đức Phật nói ra
to the Tushita Heaven, meaning
mà được lên Cung trời đâu xất Tức là
we get to see the Maitreya Buddha, my
chúng ta được diễn Kiến Đức Phật di nặc
dear fellow practitioners! Oh my, what could be better? So just
các quý đạo hữu ạ Ui giời ơi còn gì bằng
stay within the Six
nữa phải không nên cứ ở trong pháp Lục
Harmonies; it's unimaginable, it's incredibly
Hòa thôi nó không thể nghĩ bàn nó quá
victorious, my dear fellow practitioners! And
thủ thắng luôn các quý Đạo ữu ạ Mà chúng
we must know that the Tushita Heaven is the
ta phải biết là cung trời đâu rất là
most wonderful and beneficial heaven, my dear fellow
cung Trời tuyệt vời hời nhất rồi có quý
practitioners, it guides us to the right path.
Đạo hữ ạ cho chúng ta đi đúng pháp rồi
Therefore, only when the mind is illuminated by the Han Guan will we
Thế cho nên tâm chiếu Hàn quán mới mới
realize that what we have said before
biết là ô cái lời nói của mình từ trước
is right.  It's a rare opportunity to
đến nay là phải hy hữu duyên lắm mới gặp
encounter the Six Harmonies Dharma, and that's true because with a
được pháp Lục Hòa là đúng bởi vì là tâm
focused mind, we only see ourselves practicing the Six Harmonies.
chế quán chỉ thấy mình tu Lục Hòa chúng
We see so many miraculous things, so
ta thấy được rất là nhiều chuyện rất là
many wondrous things. And
nhiều điều Nhiệm Màu Và cái cái cái cái
our cultivation capacity is
cái cái cái năng lực tu của mình ấy nó
developed because we diligently
được phát triển nên do chúng ta chăm chỉ
practice, the fire of wisdom is opened. You
thực hành luộc hỏa trí tuệ khai mở các
see, with a focused mind, we can
quý đạo hữu thấy là tâm chếu ă quán hầu
do almost anything. We're always the
như vào việc gì cũng làm được Không việc
ones teaching, so the
gì cũng là người dạy nhá cho nên đến cái
saying goes, "Those who practice the Six Harmonies always act as
câu là người tu Lục Hòa luôn làm thầy
guides." That's right, I
dẫn đường ô thôi Đúng rồi cái này mình
've proven this with my own experience.
đã là là được chứng minh bằng của mình
From childhood to adulthood, I've
rồi tâm chiếu Hoàn quán từ nhỏ đến lớn
never had to stand under a master in any assembly.
chưa đến hội chúng nào mà phải đứng dưới
Even among Buddhists, I've always been the most respected, even in
trên hàng phật tử cũng là đứng trên đi
school, I've been the class leader.
học làm lớp trưởng đến đâu cũng là người
No matter where the assembly is, the
được coi trọng nhất dù là cái hội chúng
focused mind always
đấy đến đâu thì tâm chiếu Hàn quán vẫn
stands above. It turns out that when we practice the Six Harmonies, when we
đứng trên hóa ra là mình tu Lục Hòa đến
enter into the Buddha's teachings,
lúc vào cái cái lời dạy của đức Phật ấy
practicing the Six Harmonies and acting as guides is absolutely correct. That's wonderful!
tu Lục Hòa làm thầy dẫn đường ô chuẩn
Do you see, dear friends, that with a focused
luôn Hay quá C Quý đợ Hữu thấy không cho
mind, even if you say, "
nên tâm chứ quán nói là dù là có bảo là
Now I want..."  To practice the Six Harmonies, one must pour
bây giờ muốn tu Lục Hòa phải đổ nước
copper water into the mouth of the mind, the mind of the Bodhisattva, and the Bodhisattva, and the Bodhisattva,
đồng vào miệng tâm chiếu m quán Đồng Ý
to have one's heart, brains, and eyes gouged out to practice the Six Harmonies. The mind
Ngà moi tim móc óc móc mắt để được tu
and soul of the Bodhisattva also agreed, the
Lục Hòa tâm ch hồn quán cũng đồng ý ngài
young man, even if his bones and flesh were stripped away to practice the Six Harmonies,
trẻ xương dóc thịt để được tu lục hỏa
he would still
ngài hạnh phúc lắm các quý đạo hữu ạ rất
agree. He was so happy, dear fellow practitioners, so incredibly happy, it's beyond comprehension. So, the Bodhisattva told you, dear fellow practitioners, about the moment when the mind of the Bodhisattva began to practice, when he started walking, walking, walking, walking, practicing. His husband said, "I will tell my
thì chồng có bảo này này là anh sẽ bảo
parents," but the mind was too strong, and he said, "They
bố mẹ xong là tâm chế quá bảo bố mẹ cũng
can't dissuade me because they don't know about this good deed yet,
không khuyên được vì việc tốt này bố mẹ
so I'll just keep practicing. They'll
chưa biết cho nên cứ tu thời gian bố mẹ
know later." So, his parents said, "Even if you tell them to stop practicing, I can
khác biết cho nên bố mẹ bảo anh có bảo
never
bố mẹ Khuyên bỏ tu cũng không bao giờ
tell you that." Then he said, "I
bảo em được điều đó xong bảo bảo lên
'll go to the Master," and said, "If the
Thầy bảo sẽ lên Thầy bảo bảo nếu mà thầy
Master tells me to stop practicing, I'll leave him." That's it, I'm doomed. My
Bảo Khuyên không tu nữa thì bỏ thầy luôn
husband is
không đó thế là chịu chết luôn đấy Chồng
doomed because this is the ultimate goal.
chịu chết luôn bởi vì đây nó là cái Cứu
So when the mind of the Bodhisattva
cánh rồi cho nên khi tâm chiếu quá gặp
encountered the Dharma, he realized that
được pháp mới thấy rằng trên thế gian
no one in this world has ever been able to say what the Buddha said,
này chưa có ai nói được điều mà Phật nói
so there's no place for it.  What could be better than that?
cho nên là không thể nào có chỗ nào hơn
Therefore, we must practice. There's no
được nữa cho nên là ta phải tu không có
reason to abandon our husband, our
lý do gì ta phải bỏ bỏ chồng thì bỏ bỏ
family, our possessions, or our practice. We ca
gia đình thì bỏ bỏ tài sản thì bỏ bỏ tu
n't abandon our practice. And then, I
không bỏ không thể bỏ tu được thế mà vào
heard the master say something
một cái lại được nghe sư phụ nói một câu
about the Six Harmonies, and I truly understood the Six Harmonies, my dear fellow
về Lục Hòa mà mình thực Hà Lục Hòa được
practitioners. I only heard it through my ears,
đấy các quý đạo hữu ạ chỉ nghe qua tai
like some people hear it through their ears,
thôi nhá như có người thì nghe qua tai
but with focused concentration, it penetrates my ears. My
nhưng tâm chú quán là nghe lọt vàoo tai
dear friends, the master is talking to
quý đợ Hữu ạ sư phụ là nói chuyện với
guests. He's been to many places, but
khách là sư phụ có đi ở nhiều chỗ nhưng
it wasn't as harmonious as this. So, the
nó không được cục hòa như vậy cho nên là
master wants to establish a Six
sư phụ muốn là ra đây kiến lập một pháp
Harmonies Dharma Assembly here. When the master talks to
Hội Lục Hòa Ơ t Sư phụ nói chuyện với
others, his mind is focused on doing meritorious work somewhere, and he
người khác tâm chiếu hòn quán đang làm
hears it.
công quả chỗ kia nghe thấy cái tâm là sư
Naturally,
phụ muốn một cái tự nhiên làm sao nó lại
that sentence penetrates his ears. Even the whole
lọt luôn vào tai mình cái câu đấy còn cả
conversation the master has with guests, that
câu chuyện mà Sư phụ nói với khách chả
sentence just penetrates
câu là lọt vào tai chả để ý gì mà đến
his ears without him paying attention. Is
câu đấy nó lọt vào tai mình hay chưa ký
n't that right, my dear friends? And with unwavering determination,
đợ Hữu thế ha chưa Thế và kiên định luôn
establishing the Dharma assembly, harmony is achieved, and
lập ra đạo tràng cái là được hòa luôn và
in the intention, the mind is focused on concentration.  So, if
trong ý định là tâm ch quán nói là Ơ thế
I practice the Six Harmonies like this, and I guide the
Mình lục hò như thế thì mình hướng dẫn
Buddhists, then I'm the head of the Dharma center, and
cho phật tử thế Mình đạo tràng trưởng
no one dares to say anything to me. Then
không ai dám nói mình thì sao Thế thì
I'll create more Dharma centers so that the
mình lập ra cho nó có nhiều đạo tràng để
Dharma center head and I
đạo tràng Trưởng mới mình lục hò với
can practice the Six Harmonies together. Do you see? But in the end, we still have to rise up; we're not always below anyone. Do you see, dear Dharma friends? That's why the Six Harmonies Dharma is wonderful. Whatever we want to do,
Hòa là tuyệt vời muốn làm gì tâm chúng
whatever our minds are directed towards, we must be the
ta hướng làm gì thì phải làm người trên
highest, it's impossible not to be able to. Do you
nhất không thể nào không được các quý
understand that, dear Dharma friends? That's why we must
đạo hiểu thế cho nên là phải phải phải
practice. This is very precious, dear Dharma friends. It's
tu Cái này là quý lắm các quý đạo hữu ạ
truly a rare opportunity from countless lifetimes. I
thật là hy hữu duyên từ vô lượng kiếp
don't know what good roots I planted, but
bây giờ không biết trồng căn lành nào mà
now I've encountered the Six Harmonies Dharma and am
bây giờ lại gặp được pháp lục hỏa lại
practicing within the assembly of Six Harmonies. With a mind that illuminates the perfect contemplation, I
được tu trong hội chúng lục hỏa đấy tâm
joyfully say to the Buddha, "
chiếu Hoàn quán vẫn hoan hỉ bạch Phật
I don't understand why
như thế Con không hiểu nổi Tại sao mà
my first karmic connection is to
cái nhân duyên đầu tiên của con mà con
practice this solitary harmony. It's the karmic
lại được Tu độc hòa thế này nó là nhân
connection to become a fully enlightened being,
duyên làm chính đẳng chính giác cơ mà
not just an Arhat." It's so
chứ không phải là chỉ là A la hán các
rare, that's why the
quý đã ý ạ hy hữu như thế cho nên tâm
mind says, "Anyone who leaves the Six Harmonies Dharma is
chú quán nói rằng ai rời pháp Lục Hòa
truly too..."  So foolish, so incredibly foolish! Anyone who is
quả thật là quá dại quá dại luôn a ai mà
steadfast in the Six Harmonious Principles,
kiên định trong pháp Lục Hòa chúng ta
remember that in the next life we ​​will meet again in the
nhớ là kiếp tới là gặp nhau trên cung
heavenly realm. Even if you are not
trời đâu xuất quý đ như thấy không kiên
steadfast in the Six Harmonious Principles, you will still meet again in the heavenly realm.
định trong pháp Lục Hòa là phải gặp nhau
Even if you go up
nh trên cung trời đu xất dù đó lên nên
there, pay homage to the Maitreya Buddha, then go down to the
đó đảnh lễ đức Phật Di Lặc xong Xem cung
heavenly realm and immediately return to
trời đâu xất Cái xuống luôn lại đi làm
your duties, right? That's good, so you are very happy, not unhappy at all. The mind is focused and mindful. Very happy. Even if you talk for one day, seven days, 24 hours a day without stopping, the joyful mind of the
thì vẫn không giảm đ cái tâm hoan hỉ của
Six Harmonious Principles will not diminish. This year, next year, for your whole
qu pháp l h năm nay nói sang năm nói cả
life, the joyful mind will remain
cuộc đời này nói thì tâm hoan hỉ nó vẫn
in this state. Very
ở nguyên một trạng thái này rất là hạnh
happy, dear Dharma friends! Therefore, the Six
phúc các quý Đạo hếu ạ Cho nên pháp Lục
Harmonious Principles are extremely precious. If you were to
Hòa là vô cùng cao quý Nếu như mà có
use any worldly words, no
dùng từ thế gian nào nữa cũng không có
words could describe it. You can
từ nào có thể tả được các quý đạo hữu nó
only use your own heart to describe it, because
chỉ dùng tâm mình thôi để mà tả thôi vì
your heart has no language. I
tâm mình nó không có ngôn ngữ được tôi
cannot express all the language
không thể nói được hết cái ngôn ngữ
in my heart. It is so incredibly
trong tâm của tôi ra được nó rất là hạnh
happy, dear Dharma friends!  Oh, I'm extremely
phúc như thế các quý đợ ạ vô cùng hạnh
happy! So,
phúc nhá Cho nên là cái chương trình tu
this year's practice program is absolutely wonderful, dear fellow
của năm nay là quá tuyệt vời luôn các
practitioners! It's truly amazing!
quý Đạ Hữu ạ rất là tuyệt vời thế cho
Therefore, I sincerely hope that all of you will
nên tâm chú Hàn quán Rất mong muốn các
diligently practice. Whether we
quý đạo hữu chúng ta tinh tấn nhá Muốn
meet the Buddha or not is up to us. If we
gặp phật hay không là ở chúng ta thôi
want to reach the Upper Heaven, we should
nhá muốn nên Cung trời đôu xuất hàng
listen to the Dharma every day and then do our duties. It's
ngày nghe pháp rồi đi làm phận sự Nó
wonderful, dear fellow practitioners! It's wonderful
thích lắm các quý đạo hữu ạ nhá thích
because we are joyful in our hearts. We
lắm là do mình hoan hỉ trong tâm mình
know that the Bodhisattva Protector of the
biết là như thế nên Bồ Tát hộ Minh ở
Upper Heaven descends to the Upper Heaven.
trên cung trời đâu sốt xuống các vị tất
All the Buddhas in the last eon are in the Upper
cả các vị phật ở kiếp cuối cùng đều trên
Heaven, dear fellow practitioners. And yet,
cung trời đôu xất các quý đạo hữu ạ Thế
we cultivate this little bit of merit,
mà chúng ta tu một ít ỏi công đức này có
what is there to gain? Just steadfastly practicing harmony every day, and we
cái gì đâu hàng ngày kiên định độ hòa
can reach the Upper Heaven.
thôi mà được lên Cung trời đâu xất thì
What could be better than that, right? We
còn gì bằng nữa phải không Thế chúng ta
have such rare karmic connections.
là nhân duyên hy hữu lắm th biết được
Knowing this means enlightenment, dear fellow
điều này biết tức là giác ngộ đấy các
practitioners. Enlightenment of cause and effect. But after
quý đạo hiếu ạ giác ngộ nhân quả thế mà
enlightenment, we don't go to work.
giác ngộ rồi không chịu đi làm thôi hôm
Today, I have to go out with my husband,
nay con là phải đi chơi với chồng con
so I can't practice the Six Harmonies. Isn't that a
cho nên không tu Lục Hòa được Có phải
pity?
tiếc không phải
Not going to work means not practicing the Six Harmonies.  It's
không đi làm gì mà không tu Lục Hòa được
incredibly wasteful, extremely wasteful!
rất là lãng phí lãng phí vô cùng nhá Cho
Therefore, I, the Abbot, hope that all esteemed Dharma friends will diligently practice the
nên tâm Chú Bàn quán mong các quý đạo
principle of "harmony" and use
hữu tinh tấn độc Hòa và lấy cái tinh tấn
this diligence to cultivate a wide network of connections with all sentient beings, so that they may become part of
độc Hòa này kết duyên rộng với chúng
your community
sinh để cho chúng sinh làm hội chúng của
in the future. That's how you gain benefit and
mình sau này nhá Đấy được lợi ích được
liberation. I, the Abbot, hope that all esteemed
giải thoát nha tâm chú quán chú có quý
Dharma friends will have this spirit. Namo Buddha
đạo hữu tinh thấn Nam Mô Phật Bổn Sư
Shakyamuni!
Thích Ca Mâu
[Music]
[âm nhạc]